Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2. 2015 accrual: Against the Tide, Down On The Farm, In History's Wake, and Voices From The Waterfront photographs, March 26, 2005 through December 4, 2013, afc2013031_dc002; 841 TIFF, 4 pdf, 4 xls, and 1 m2t
  - Subseries 3. In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI files, April 8, 2008 through 2010, 264 TIFF, 1 pdf, 1 xls
    - Aaron Taylor works on the control lines leading to the nozzle as Devin Ferreira holds twine in place, July 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Aaron Taylor works on the control lines leading to the nozzle as Devin Ferreira holds twine in place. The nozzle controls the passage of fish both into and out of the parlor. While some fish find their way back out of the trap through this opening, most do not. Should trap fishermen reach their daily quota, they can simply leave fish swimming in the trap, without harm, until the next day. Aaron Taylor left, Devin Ferreira right.
    - Stephen Menard works his section of the parlor, June 26, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Stephen Menard works his section of the parlor. The heavy steel and aluminum longboats make very stable platforms from which to work the traps. While designed to carry fish in the days before engines, most of the loading today is along their rails as crew haul both twine and fish to the surface. Smaller boats could not successfully resist these rotational forces.
    - Roland Smith (Bucky), Jim Main, and Rick Cambio work together to keep fish moving towards the Bucolo, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Roland Smith (Bucky), Jim Main, and Rick Cambio work together to keep fish moving towards the Bucolo. They are reducing the area available to fish swimming within the trap, eventually leaving them with no room to escape the bull net used to hoist them to the deck. At this point, crew begin to see what types of fish they have, as the water is now shallow enough for them to be visible from above. The migratory patterns of certain species are remarkably precise, and fish arrive at trap sites generally within a week or two each year as they have for the past hundred. Because of this, fishermen must be ready, or risk losing a major portion of their yearly income. Uncooperative weather at this time of the year leads to worry over their ability to get their traps in place on time. Once the traps are set, however, they look forward to the arrival of great schools of scup, one of their most important species. Left to Right: Roland Smith (Bucky), Jim Main, Rick Cambio.
    - Tom Hoxsie pulling twine in the rain, July 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Tom Hoxsie pulling twine in the rain. While in general, commercial fishing seldom stops because of weather, extremely rough days can keep trap fishermen from emptying their nets. The heavy longboats endanger crews' hands and fingers when crashing together as the catch is hardened. Two of Tom's traps are within the breakwaters at the mouth of Point Judith, often providing enough protection from summer storms to allow him to fish while others wait.
    - A skate swims near the ocean's surface, searching to escape its predicament, May 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A skate swims near the ocean's surface, searching to escape its predicament. When current regulations allow, skates are generally used as lobster bait, although the "wings" on large skate are suitable for human consumption. Proving too big for the former and too small for the latter, this fish was tossed overboard to swim away and resume its normal life.
    - Saul Umana relaxes on the short trip to the site, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Saul Umana relaxes on the short trip to the site. Trap fishermen leave their docks to begin the day's work at first light, usually between 5:30 and 7:00, depending on the time of year or the captain's inclination. When fish such as scup, striped bass or squid migrate through, crews work six or seven days a week as the majority of their income depends upon these fish. In the middle of the summer, trapping usually slows, and fishermen may skip a day between visits to give traps time to fill.
    - While modern technology has made fishing easier in many ways, it is still heavily dependent upon manual labor, August 13, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      While modern technology has made fishing easier in many ways, it is still heavily dependent upon manual labor. Trap fishing remains one of the most elemental of all the commercial fishing technologies, where large groups of men still pull nets by hand. There is a certain beauty in the work they do, although this is more readily appreciated by those not involved in the actual toil.
    - The North Star's crew finish hardening the catch, April 26, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The North Star's crew finish hardening the catch. The fish, consisting mostly of pogies, are packed into the little remaining net left to them. To help with the process, Tom slides large dowels through the twine and between the rails of the skiff. These dowels act as spare hands, holding the net they have managed to pull aboard against the struggling fish. Pogies seen making it over the net have only temporarily escaped; they remain in the parlor and are gathered the following day. Tom's traps are well located for catching pogies on their migratory path, although their appearance can seem a mixed blessing. Not overly valuable, they are primarily used as bait, but still provide income with the large numbers caught. To the unaccustomed, it is a spectacular sight when thousands thrash the water to a froth as they are forced to the surface. Raised and dumped into the boat, they make a memorable cacophony as their tails slap the North Star's deck. Left to right: Tom Hoxsie, Sam Willis, Ian Campbell.
    - Gulls are constant, if unwelcome, companions to all fishermen, July 14, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Gulls are constant, if unwelcome, companions to all fishermen. Remarkably adaptable and clever, not to mention eternally hungry, they take full advantage of any situation where they may steal a free lunch. Pilfering is kept to a minimum, however, as there are generally enough crewmen on deck to keep them at bay. Nonetheless, they occasionally swoop in to grab fish from open totes when opportunity calls.
    - Aaron Taylor flips a bluefish stuck in the twine back into the trap, July 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Aaron Taylor flips a bluefish stuck in the twine back into the trap. Fishermen treat bluefish and their teeth with a healthy dose of respect. Bandaged hands are commonplace as crews handle thousands of them over the course of the season. Frenzied schools of blues can shred the trap's netting, although this was more of a problem in the past when twine was made of cotton.
    - Bucky and Jim haul twine, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Bucky and Jim haul twine. As with many still in the industry, fishing has been a lifelong pursuit. Both men have spent the larger portion of their careers far off Rhode Island's coast on trawlers and swordfish boats. The draggerman's lifestyle is markedly different. Trips lasting anywhere from five to ten days at sea keep them far from home, making family life difficult for all concerned. Trap fishing has become the perfect way for fishermen to do what they know and love without the disadvantages offshore work entails. Trips are short and end where they began every day. The trap season also closes before cold temperatures blanket the region, and while the work is hard, it is not carried out around the clock as it is at sea. For young crewmen, trapping can be the beginning of a career or a summer's job, tiding them over as they plan their next move. Like all outdoor jobs, there are people who fish because they dread a working life surrounded by walls. Fishing offers an alternative to the typical nine-to-five job many others enjoy. Roland Smith (Bucky) left, James Main right.
    - Rain pelts Sam Willis as the pot-hauler takes the weight of the head-end of the parlor through this block—the same block used to raise lobster traps once the fishing season ends, August 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
    - Portrait of Thomas Hinckley, August 13, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Portrait of Thomas Hinckley. Tom has worked for Alan Glidden for a number of seasons on the Amelia Bucolo, and is seen here concentrating on the work at hand. Having spent many years in Central America, Tom speaks Spanish fluently and uses it on a daily basis while chatting with Saul Umana, a transplant from El Salvador.
    - Bucky climbs aboard the Amelia Bucolo, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Bucky climbs aboard the Amelia Bucolo. At this point, the net has been hardened and the fish are ready to bail from the trap. Bucky returns to the deck to help land and sort the catch. The other three: Nick Lord, Tom Hinckley, and Rick Cambio remain in the longboat, continuously hardening the net as others remove the fish. Trap fishing is much like opening a grab bag. Except for times when the entire catch is composed of a single species, most days offer a variety. On any given day, the nets may include scup, albacore, striped bass, sea bass, flounder, skate, dogfish, butterfish, menhaden, false albacore, ocean sunfish, squid, whitefish, weakfish, stingray, blackfish, fluke, eel, sea robin, or any other number of species. One exciting day, an enormous tuna entered a trap at Sakonnet Point. Once a common occurrence, fishermen noted this was unlikely to happen again for another dozen years. On another day, this particular crew found a great white shark swimming in their trap. Fortunately, the fish seemed subdued by the time the crew arrived and released it back into the sea. Left to right: Nick Lord, James Main, Roland Smith, Thomas Hinckley, Rich Cambio.
    - Alan Glidden, after closing the nozzle, begins to haul the trap itself, October 9, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Alan Glidden, after closing the nozzle, begins to haul the trap itself. Alan's enthusiasm for trap fishing stems from both the green nature of the fishery as a whole, and from the quality of the fish they produce. Scooped from the ocean as if it were nothing more than an oversized aquarium, fish are seldom damaged as they are with other methodologies.
    - The entire crew hardens the catch against the starboard side of the Maria Mendonsa, April 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The entire crew hardens the catch against the starboard side of the Maria Mendonsa. In the heyday of trap fishing, when over a hundred men might have worked for one company, this would have been considered a small crew. Alan Wheeler's crew count rises and falls to match his needs.
    - The bull net, capable of lifting nearly a thousand pounds of fish, is raised and lowered by the ship's winch, off-camera in this shot, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The bull net, capable of lifting nearly a thousand pounds of fish, is raised and lowered by the ship's winch, off-camera in this shot. Nick Lord, handling the net, will swing it overboard where men in the longboat guide it into the thick of the catch. When full, Nick gives a shout to the man tending the winch to lift them aboard. Crew in the longboats guide the net over the rail, and once cleared, the weight of the fish swings the load to the other side of the vessel. Everyone on deck is careful to stand clear, as there is little chance of halting its swing. The bull net's clever design allows it to open under load, something that helps fishermen quickly empty the trap. The bottom of the net purses together with chain. At the right moment, Nick releases this pursing, dumping the fish on deck where they are sorted into baskets, totes, and barrels. Left to right: Thomas Hinclkey, Nick Lord, Saul Umana, Rick Cambio (seated) Roland Smith, Alan Glidden.
    - Thousands of menhaden thrash the little bit of ocean left to them, April 26, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Thousands of menhaden thrash the little bit of ocean left to them. This species seems to have more names than any other found in New England, a reflection perhaps of their widely ranging habitat. The Atlantic menhaden, also called mossback or bunker, swims in waters from Nova Scotia to the coast of Florida. Usually referred to locally as pogies, they die easily and spoil rapidly. Beyond that, they are oily and bony creatures generally unfit for human consumption, although they are processed for their Omega-3 oils. Pogies school by the millions while out to sea, and when they hit, fill traps quite rapidly. While trappers sell them as bait, larger fishing operations seining for menhaden sell them as a food source for other animals such as pigs, chickens, household pets, or farm-raised fish such as salmon.
    - Sully leans against the winch drum as he watches the coastline pass by, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sully leans against the winch drum as he watches the coastline pass by. The winch is one of the more important pieces of gear on the boat, responsible for all of the heavy lifting. Note the deep grooves worn into the drum's bronze surface by rope bearing heavy loads, a true measure of the work done by this machine over many years of operation. Alfred Sullivan.
    - Between each pass of the bull net, the crew continues condensing the fish still within the trap, July 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Between each pass of the bull net, the crew continues condensing the fish still within the trap. The port deck of the vessel has been heavily loaded, so the remaining fish will go to the starboard side to keep her on an even keel. This trip consisted largely of striped bass and bluefish, with the usual handful of other species. The aft deck of this boat, as with all large fishing vessels, is readily divided into pens. This makes a convenient way to separate species, but more importantly, it keeps thousands of pounds of slippery fish from careening across the deck in rough weather. Not only dangerous to crew caught in the avalanche, this quick shift of weight can dangerously affect the stability of the ship itself.
    - Striped bass are highly prized, to both sports and commercial fishermen alike, June 18, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Striped bass are highly prized, to both sports and commercial fishermen alike. Because of this, heated controversy surrounds this particular species. Local sportsmen prefer stripers to almost all other finfish and feel commercial ventures cut into their share of fun. The Rhode Island Fisheries Management Report for this year sheds interesting light on the technologies used to catch them. In 2008, the quota for striped bass in Rhode Island was divided between floating trap fishermen, who were allowed 40 percent of the annual quota, and rod and reelers, who took a 60 percent share of the allowed catch. In that year, the rod and reel quota of 145,918 pounds was taken in a mere 20 days, while trap fishermen took most of the summer to fill their quota of 97,450 pounds, a reflection of the relatively passive nature of the fishery. By law, commercial fishermen must record every striped bass they catch on a daily basis, turning over their logs to a fisheries management agency each week to assure an accurate account of the fish taken. In addition, they must place a trap tag through the mouth and gills of each bass caught or face significant fines. Fishermen place these tags long before their boats reach the dock to insure themselves against harsh penalties.
    - Sam Willis empties the trap's contents onto the sorting table aboard the North Star, July 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sam Willis empties the trap's contents onto the sorting table aboard the North Star. A longtime crewmember on the boat, Sam works as a fisherman during the trapping season and heads south to work on his family's cattle ranch for the remainder of the year. Originally designed to fish for lobsters, North Star works well as a trap boat. Built of fiberglass, she has lower maintenance requirements than those of either wooden or steel vessels. While somewhat small for their biggest day's fishing, her size helps keep overhead costs low. It is also easy for Tom to switch fisheries at the end of the trapping season; he simply removes the portable sorting table and loads the boat with lobster traps. As with most people working within the industry, Tom is largely self-sufficient. To survive financially, fishermen don't have the luxury of calling in outside tradesmen to fix problems arising on a near-daily basis. Beyond mending their own nets, fishermen repair their own engines, mechanical and electrical systems, and other essential gear. They construct their own skiffs and pull worn hull plating from workboats before welding on new. Fishermen design and build new gear to make life easier, safer, or in difficult economic times, more efficient, all while operating a successful fishing business.
    - Sam hoists a stingray from the trap as Tom holds its tail to control its movements, July 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sam hoists a stingray from the trap as Tom holds its tail to control its movements. Once raised high enough, Ian will pull the net away from the hull to allow the fish to slip between it and the boat when released. Stingrays are also treated with caution, as their whip-like tails conceal a dangerously large and serrated barb with which they strike. Much larger rays than this have been pulled from the trap. Left to right: Ian Campbell, Tom Hoxsie, Sam Willis.
    - Scup, also known as porgies, are one of the most valuable species, much as they were to fishermen working the coastline in the 1800s, July 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Scup, also known as porgies, are one of the most valuable species, much as they were to fishermen working the coastline in the 1800s. Ranging from Cape Cod to South Carolina, they are known for their light taste and the fight they give when hooked. Spawned near the inner-continental shelf, the highly buoyant eggs drift to protected coastal waters. The average porgie weighs between one and two pounds and matures between two and three years of age, but can reach three to four pounds and lengths of up to eighteen inches. A homely fish with a large forehead and a small mouth, the bodies are a dull silvery color with traces of light blue throughout. A series of horizontal lines run the length of their bodies, and they are topped with a spiny dorsal fin. Scup winter in deep waters, between the middle and outer continental shelves, only returning to the Rhode Island coast as the waters warm. In one remarkable run, George Mendonsa recalled removing 100,000 pounds each day for an entire month from a single trap. Today, trap fishermen try to stretch their quota over the entire length of the scup run, helping to maintain market prices by not exceeding demand.
    - Dreary weather does not dampen Ian Campbell's enthusiasm for the day as they harden the net on the West Wall trap, August 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Dreary weather does not dampen Ian Campbell's enthusiasm for the day as they harden the net on the West Wall trap. Ian spent this summer working as a fisherman on North Star as a break from his job as a firefighter in the West. His cousin, Nick Lord, works as crew on the Amelia Bucolo.
    - The Bucolo is shown here tied to the head of the trap at Black Rock, east of Point Judith, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Bucolo is shown here tied to the head of the trap at Black Rock, east of Point Judith. The seven-member crew is aft, sorting fish they have taken from the nets. There are relatively few places left in the United States where trap fishing still occurs, and while the smallest state in the union, Rhode Island leads the nation in trap sites. Nearly half of the sites in the country are within this state, with the majority of them between Newport and Sakonnet Point.
    - Anthony Parascandolo wrestles an American torpedo back overboard, June 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Anthony Parascandolo wrestles an American torpedo back overboard. This unusual fish has been plentiful in Rhode Island waters in recent summers. Of no commercial value, these large and blubbery animals easily reach hundreds of pounds, and fishermen handle them with kid, if not rubber, gloves. Although not as famous as the electric eel, the torpedo can discharge a shock of nearly 200 volts.
    - Ian stands ankle deep in menhaden on the deck of the North Star, April 26, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Ian stands ankle deep in menhaden on the deck of the North Star. The brightly silvered pogie has a distinctive spot behind each gill. Striped bass, bluefish, sharks, mackerel, and tuna voraciously consume this species, as do many sea birds. Gulls, gannets, and egrets, to name a few, all take advantage of the enormous schools of this hapless fish. Popularity has many disadvantages.
    - Ian unceremoniously tosses a small striped bass back into the ocean, July 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Ian unceremoniously tosses a small striped bass back into the ocean. This removable table makes it easier for the North Star's crew to sort fish they will keep from those they return to the sea. Trapping is perhaps the greenest of the commercial fisheries, with its low fuel and refrigeration requirements. More importantly, however, is the nearly complete lack of bycatch. Fish caught in the trap that fishermen are not allowed to keep are known as bycatch. They may be too small, like the striper in the photograph, not edible, or simply not allowed under current regulations. In trapping, fishermen sort the catch as it is brought onto the deck. Unwanted fish go back overboard and swim away. While there will inevitably be some fish lost, it is not unusual to see but a handful die in a catch of thousands and thousands of pounds. Trap fishermen can easily select target species from the pile and discard the rest. Ian Campbell.
    - Sam Willis at work in the skiff, May 8, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sam Willis at work in the skiff. Fishing, to most commercial fishermen, is much more than a job. The crew from the North Star keeps fishing poles aboard for use later in the day. Throwing pogies into a tote of water as they empty their traps provides them with live bait with which to tempt striped bass. Leaving the North Star tied to the trap, they often take the skiff to try their hand in fifteen minutes of sport fishing before heading home.
    - Despite the widespread use of electronics, it is still possible to find magnetic compasses on commercial fishing vessels, May 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Despite the widespread use of electronics, it is still possible to find magnetic compasses on commercial fishing vessels. Elegantly designed instruments that respond magically to invisible forces, they are often the only navigational tool needed. In deep fog, fishermen may prefer using GPS and radar to get them safely to and from their traps, but the compass has the advantage of simplicity working in its favor. When all else fails, knowledge and a compass brings them home.
    - The Maria Mendonsa turns from the trap and heads home with a deck loaded with fish, April 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF